Guide to the Max (Mac) Weiss Papers TAM.844
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Max (Mac) Weiss Papers
1934-1987
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weiss, Max
Troyan, Stephanie
TAM.844
1 linear foot in 2 manuscript boxes
Max (Mac) Weiss was the Education Director of the Communist Party of the United States of America, an editor for Political Affairs, and an author of numerous party pamphlets and articles. Weiss joined the Young Communist League (YCL) in 1928, and his entry into the Party began in 1928. He edited the YCL's national publication, The Young Worker, and served in various YCL leadership roles, including as its Education Director, New England's District Organizers, and on YCL's Executive Committee. He became the Party's District Organizer in Western Pennsylvania in 1943 and the National Education Director in 1945. He was arrested in 1955 under the "membership clause" of the Smith Act and left the Party in 1962. The Max (Mac) Weiss Papers (dated 1934-1987) consists of materials created and collected by Weiss documenting his personal life and experiences in the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). Materials include court documents from Weiss' Smith Act trial, including a copy of his testimony; original writings by Weiss; correspondence with his daughter Elinor, which documents his personal life and relationships; and correspondence after Weiss' time in the CPUSA, including correspondence with Irving Weissman, that documents his personal life, career, and politics. The collection also includes biographical materials about Weiss, including a program and register from Weiss' memorial service, and copies of City College alumni magazine that include profiles of Weiss.
Scope and Contents
The Max (Mac) Weiss Papers (dated 1934-1987) consists of materials created and collected by Weiss documenting his personal life and experiences in the Communist Party of the United States of America (CPUSA). Materials include court documents from Weiss' Smith Act trial, including a copy of his testimony; original writings by Weiss; correspondence with his daughter Elinor, which documents his personal life and relationships; and correspondence after Weiss' time in the CPUSA, including correspondence with Irving Weissman, that documents his personal life, career, and politics. The collection also includes biographical materials about Weiss, including a program and register from Weiss' memorial service, and copies of City College alumni magazine that include profiles of Weiss.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged alphabetically.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Stephanie Troyan, Executrix of Elinor Weiss' Estate, in July 2024; the accession number associated with this gift is 2025.015.
Custodial History
The collection had been maintained by Elinor (Elly) Weiss, Max Weiss' daughter, until her death. Stephanie Troyan, Elinor's cousin, serving as the Executrix of Elinor Weiss' Estate, physically transferred the collection to the home of Mimi Daitz, a historian a long-time friend of the Weiss family, until arrangements were made to place to collection in an archives.
Biographical Note
Max (Mac) Weiss was the Education Director of the Communist Party of the United States of America, an editor for Political Affairs, and an author of numerous party pamphlets and articles. Weiss joined the Young Communist League (YCL) in 1928, and his entry into the Party began in 1928. He edited the YCL's national publication, The Young Worker, and served in various YCL leadership roles, including as its Education Director, New England's District Organizers, and on YCL's Executive Committee. He became the Party's District Organizer in Western Pennsylvania in 1943 and the National Education Director in 1945. He was arrested in 1955 under the "membership clause" of the Smith Act and left the Party in 1962.
Communism -- United States.; Communist trials.; Anti-communist movements; Political persecution; Communist Party of the United States of America; Troyan, Stephanie
- Biographical Information, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- City College Alumnus Articles About Max Weiss, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence -- General, 1959-1985 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
- Correspondence -- Elinor (Elly) Weiss (Daughter), 1977-1984 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
- Correspondence -- Irving Weissman, 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
- List of Max Weiss Memorial Attendees; Memorial Register, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Pamphlets (by Weiss), 1934-1942 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Smith Act Court Case Documents, 1955-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
- Testimony, circa 1955-1962 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- Writings, 1956, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)